Part One: Introduction
Understanding
and managing pain during radiotherapy.
As you begin to undergo radiation
treatment to your head and neck.
One symptom
that is likely to present itself is pain.
In this video we will explain:
Where in your body
you may experience pain, and to assure you
that we are here to help you through it
with various pain management techniques
Mucositis: Rinses and Gargles.
One common cause of pain during radiotherapy
is a condition called mucositis.
This is when the lining of your mouth
and throat gets sore and inflamed.
To help with this, we often recommend
special rinses and gargles.
You might use something called Muguard
or even a baking soda rinse
to soothe your mouth.
We have a separate video
that explains mucositis in more detail
oral cavity or mouth pain:
special rinses and medicines.
If the pain is in your mouth,
we might suggest special rinses
or even medicines
like Doxepin or Morphine.
We have found that these medications
can be rinsed in the mouth
and spit out to give a local effect,
without causing any systemic side effects.
If it's really hard for you to eat
because of the pain,
we might give you a medicine
called lidocaine to numb the area.
We would want you to rinse and swallow
this prior to each meal, which will give
you a 15 to 20 minute window of numbness
to better eat and drink.